Guide to the Aubra Nooncaster Collection
The Wittliff Collections
Aubra Nooncaster Collection
1938-1990
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Nooncaster, Aubra
SWWC.122
2 boxes
1 Linear Feet
The Aubra Nooncaster Papers span 1938-1992, and document the writings of coach, poet, and mentor to Larry L. King, Aubra Nooncaster. The collection is arranged into four series: Correspondence, Writings about Coach Nooncaster, Nooncaster's Writings, and Larry L. King. The bulk of the collection is correspondence from Larry L. King to Nooncaster. The collection also includes published poems and unpublished drafts of poems written by Nooncaster
Scope and Contents
The collection of coach and poet, Aubra Nooncaster, spans 1938-1992; however, the bulk of the collection dates from 1980-1990. It is arranged into four series: Correspondence, Writings about Coach Nooncaster, Writings by Nooncaster, and Larry L. King. The correspondence to Nooncaster (excluding Larry L. King's letters) have been sorted alphabetically. Some letters have the original envelopes with them. Much of the correspondence references Larry L. King's article in Parade titled, "A Coach I Can't Forget" about King's time in Coach Nooncaster's class.
Published articles and reviews concerning Coach Nooncaster are in their own series. Nooncaster has published four works: Listen for a Poem, Selected Poems: 1959-1988, Amid the Glow of Suns, and Interim Days: A Book of Poems, and the collection contains many of drafts of his poetry.
The final series contains papers relating to Larry L. King, including correspondence and articles. The letters from King are arranged chronologically from 1974-1992. A few letters from Nooncaster to King have been sorted into their own folder. In addition to correspondence, the collection includes articles written by King and writings about King. The writings about King mostly concern The Best Little Whorehouse in Texas as well as his two plays "The Night Hank Williams Died" and "The Kingfisher." And finally, this series includes two photographs of King, possibly from 1971. One depicts King in front of a dilapidated house, and the second is of King with an unidentified man and children.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frances Nooncaster, 1993.
Related Materials
Larry L. King Papers (Collection 006).
Biographical Notes
Aubra Nooncaster graduated Sul Ross State College with a Master's in English in 1940. Upon returning from service in World War II, he was hired as head basketball and assistant football coach at Midland High School where he taught for two years. At Midland, Coach Nooncaster was also given an English class to teach that his football players took in anticipation of an easy A. One of these students was Larry L. King, the playwright and author best known for The Best Little Whorehouse in Texas. Nooncaster would become a great influence on Larry L. King's writing career. As early as 1974, King began a lifelong correspondence with Coach Nooncaster.
In 1947, Aubra Nooncaster began to teach at Pampa Independent School District in Pampa, Texas, where he stayed until his retirement in 1978. During his career as a teacher he pursued an enduring love of poetry, ultimately publishing four books of poems: Listen for a Poem, Selected Poems: 1959-1988, Amid the Glow of Suns, and Interim Days: A Book of Poems.
His community, peers, and former students loved and admired Aubra Nooncaster. Many of his former students reconnected with him after reading Larry L. King's article about his time with Nooncaster entitled "A Coach I Can't Forget." The article was published in Parade, a newspaper insert that ran nationwide, on July 17, 1983.
Index Terms
Subjects
Teachers -- Texas
Document Types
Correspondence
Subjects (Persons)
King, Larry L.
- Correspondence, 1959-1991
  Series Description
  The correspondence to Nooncaster (excluding Larry L. King's letters) have been sorted alphabetically. Some letters have the original envelopes with them. Much of the correspondence references Larry L. King's article in Parade titled, "A Coach I Can't Forget" about Mr. King's time in Coach Nooncaster's class.
  - Correspondence A-H (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contents
    Some of the individuals who wrote multiple letters are: Evelyn (Wemple) Allen, Bob Allford, Allen Bobroff, Eula Burkes, and Barbara Hodges
  - Correspondence I-Z, Box/Folder: 1/ (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes two photos from Nolan and Billie Jones, and one photo from Mildred Wilson.
    Some of the individuals who wrote multiple letters are Larry Jarritt, Don Laughlin, Stephen Oates, Helen Payne, and Margaret Howell Tayloe
  - Call list (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Writings about Coach Nooncaster, 1959-1988
  Published articles and reviews concerning Coach Nooncaster are in their own series. Nooncaster has published four works: Listen for a Poem, Selected Poems: 1959-1988, Amid the Glow of Suns, and Interim Days: A Book of Poems, and the collection contains many of drafts of his poetry.
  - Writings about Nooncaster (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Newspaper clipping Speech about Nooncaster as teacher Interview by son John Nooncaster about Great Depression and New Deal Book review of Interim Days Parade July 17, 1983 article, "A Coach I Can't Forget" by Larry L. King Article, "Best Little Whorehouse in Texas author, Larry King, visits an old Pampa buddy" by Julia Clark (3 copies) Article, "Players Reflect on Coaches" by Carlton Stowers
  - Published caricature of Nooncaster (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writings by Nooncaster, 1938-1988
  Nooncaster has published four works: Listen for a Poem, Selected Poems: 1959-1988, Amid the Glow of Suns, and Interim Days: A Book of Poems, and the collection contains many of drafts of his poetry.
  - Poetry (Box 1, Folder 6)
    "About a Couple of Birds Making a Nest" "Barrier" "Cathedral Peak" "A Dialogue" "Early Rancher" "ECC. 1" "A Glass Darkly" (2 drafts) "God's Way" "The Inchoate" "In Heaven" (2 copies) "Laying By" "Love in Whitman's Poetry" (term theme) "Love's Dimensions" "Love's Scope" "Nassau Bound" (2 copies) "New Year 1978" "Perhaps" "Recapture" "Replanting" "Reunion" "The Revival of Uncle Buck" (2 drafts) "Rivers" (with "To Any Librarian") (2 copies) "Rivers" "To Any Librarian" "Ten Days of April" (Sheet music) "The Trailway Tales" "Two Men of Ur" "What Fortune" (with "New Age" and "Same Wine, Same Bottle") "When I am Dead" (with "Old Men" and"Rapprochement") "A Work"
  - Untitled writings (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles by Nooncaster, 1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Athletic Journal April 1960:"The Double Wing T versus the 5-4-2"
    Athletic Journal May 1960: "The Double Wing T versus the Tight Tackle Six" (2 copies)
    The Crossroads Anthology: Grand Prize poem "June Blow-out"
    Scholastic Coach May 1960: "Offensive Trends in Texas H.S. Football"
  - Teaching aids: Definition of Poetry and teaching aid with Nooncaster's notes (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Notes (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notebooks: teaching plans and football plays (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- Awards, 1974-1975
  - "Narrative" Poem Awards presented by Showcase for Poets. Poet Lore: A National Quarterly of World Poetry: 1974 First Prize for Nooncaster's poem "Bucolics" ( with a check from Poet Lore Division of Literary Publication Foundation, Inc. to Nooncaster for $25) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Larry L. King, 1974-1992
  The final series contains papers relating to Larry L. King, including correspondence and articles. The letters from King are arranged chronologically from 1974-1992. A few letters from Nooncaster to King have been sorted into their own folder. In addition to correspondence, the collection includes articles written by King and writings about King. The writings about King mostly concern The Best Little Whorehouse in Texas as well as his two plays "The Night Hank Williams Died" and "The Kingfisher." And finally, this series includes two photographs of King, possibly from 1971. One depicts King in front of a dilapidated house, and the second is of King with an unidentified man and children.
  - Correspondence, 1974-1992
    - 1974-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Nooncaster to King (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Articles by King (excluding articles about Nooncaster), 1982-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Writings about King, 1979-1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of Larry L. King, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)